A Finding Aid to the Ary Stillman Papers, 1924-1983, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ary Stillman papers
1924-1983
Archives of American Art
Stillman, Ary, 1891-1967
AAA.stilary
Archival Resource Key
0.4 Linear feet
The papers of Ary Stillman measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1924 to 1983. The papers document his career as a painter through reminiscences, a diary, and other writings on art; a video recorded conversation with Frances Stillman on her husband Ary, a documentary on Stillman's art career, correspondence, a file of photographs of artwork, list of artwork, and other professional activity; clippings, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material.
Conditions Governing Access
Reel 1772: ACCESS RESTRICTED: written permission required.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Ary Stillman measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1924 to 1983. The papers document his career as a painter through reminiscences, a diary, and other writings on art; a video recorded conversation with Frances Stillman on her husband Ary, a documentary on Stillman's art career, correspondence, a file of photographs of artwork, list of artwork, and other professional activity; clippings, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 99-100, 1773 available for use at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. 35mm microfilm reel 1772 is unavailable through interlibrary loan until restriction is lifted.
Biographical / Historical
Ary Stillman (1891-1967) was painter in New York, N.Y. He was born in Russia and emigrated to the United States as a child. He studied at the Art Institute of Chicago and the National Academy of Design. In 1921 he moved to Paris and participated in numerous exhibitions there over the next twelve years. Stillman returned to the United States in 1933. When the horrors of the Holocaust were revealed, Stillman shifted his focus to abstract works, and by 1948, his work was completely non-objective. Stillman died in 1967. The Stillman-Lack Foundation was founded after his death in accordance with his wishes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papters were donated in 1967 and 1980 by Frances Stillman, Ary Stillman's widow and president of the Stillman-Lack Foundation (http://www.stillmanlack.org/); she donated the videos in 1985. Material on reel 1772 and the scrapbook on reel 1773 were lent for microfilming by the Stillman-Lack Foundation, 1980.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm material lent for microfilming (reels 1772-1773) including correspondence, 1976-1979, between Frances Stillman and Clement Greenberg regarding Ary's work; a 109 page reminiscence, dictated by Stillman and supplemented by Frances, covering his early life, his move to the United States, and subsequent trips abroad; excerpts from Frances' diary; and Stillman's remarks about his art. Loaned materials were returned to the Stillman-Lack Foundation in Houston, Texas and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series.
Series 1: Writings, 1928-1952 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Professional Activity Files, 1944-1983 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1924-1979 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Video recordings; Interviews; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Diaries; Stillman, Frances Fribourg; Stillman-Lack Foundation
- Writings, 1928-1952; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Writings include reminiscences by Stillman, a diary of his travels in Europe in 1952, writings on art, and articles on Stillman by others.
  - Reminiscences, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Movement", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Remarks on Painting", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diary of European Travels, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - On Stillman, 1928-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Professional Activity Files, 1944-1983; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Professional material includes a biographical outline, a file of correspondence, a file of photographs of Stillman's artwork, a list of of artwork, a video documentary of Stillman's art career, and a video conversation with Frances Stillman on her husband, Ary.
  - Biographical Outline, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of Works, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Ary Stillman Paintings/Sid Lasher Conversation with Frances Stillman", 1983 May 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 1)
    This video recording is a duplicate of an original produced in 1969.
  - "Ary Stillman: 58 Years of Painting", 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 2)
  - Photographs, Artwork, 1950-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1924-1979; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition catalogs, and a xerox copy of a chapter on Stillman for Jacometti's book "Tetes De Montparnasse"
  - Clippings, 1924-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1924-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Xerox of Jacometti's "Tetes De Montparnasse," Stillman Chapter, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)